A Guide to the Mary L. Geschwind Papers, 1845-2006
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Mary L. Geschwind Papers, 1845-2006
The Library of Virginia
50461
20.7 cubic feet (47 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mary L. Geschwind, Richmond.
Biographical Information
Anton Guenther Bernhard Osterbind was born in Atens, Oldenburg, Germany on 10 June 1820. He emigrated to the United States around 1838, and settled in Richmond, Virginia. He married 1) Mary Ann Copeland (1817-1860) on 19 September 1842, and 2) Sarah J. Jordan (1827-1919) on 25 December 1860. Osterbind was a ironworker and foreman at Tredegar Iron Works. He died in Richmond on 17 September 1919 and is buried in Hollywood Cemetery. His son, Henry Carter Osterbind, was born on 19 April 1851 in Richmond. He also worked at Tredegar Iron Works. He married Ellen Jane Clarke (1852-1928) in Goochland County, Virginia on 25 November 1875. Henry Carter Osterbind died on 1 August 1914 and is buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Their daughter, Mary Copeland Osterbind, was born in Goochland County, Virginia on 9 December 1876. She married William Frederick Haase (1877-1967), owner of a fur business begun by his father in Richmond, on 25 June 1902. Her sister, Minnie Guenther Osterbind (1879-1952) married Dr. Arthur Stevens Kimball (1878-1921). They resided in Battle Creek, Michigan. Mary O. Haase died on 14 December 1935 in Richmond, and is buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Their daughter, Margaret Ruppert Haase, was born in Richmond on 16 April 1903. She attended Randolph-Macon Woman's College and the University of Virginia. She married Dr. James Burdine Looper (1899-1950) on 25 August 1927. He was a professor and dean of the medical school at the University of Mississippi. Following Dr. Looper's death, Margaret married Joseph Foster Woodard (b. 1909) on 14 February 1960. She died in Richmond on 23 June 1982, and is buried in Forest Lawn Cemetery.
Her daughter, Mary MacAdam Looper, was born in Oxford, Lafayette County, Mississippi on 3 March 1932. She attended the University of Mississippi, where she met her husband, Herman Geschwind (1930-2006) of Kassell, Germany. They were married in Wiesbaden, Germany on 21 January 1953. They lived in various places, including Greensboro, North Carolina and St. Gallen, Switzerland, where he was employed by Burlington Industries. Mary L. Geschwind died 3 June 2017 in Henrico County, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1845-2006, of Mary Looper Geschwind (1932-2017) of Richmond, Virginia, containing genealogical research files and personal papers of the Osterbind, Haase, Looper, and Geschwind families of Richmond, Virginia, Mississippi, South Carolina, and Germany and Russia. The collection includes abstracts and transcriptions of church and court records, accounts and receipts, artwork, brochures, class notes, clippings, correspondence, estate administration records, family group sheets, genealogical notes and charts, greeting cards, invitations, obituaries, pedigree charts, photographs, postcards, programs, published sources, sheet music, sympathy cards and notes, tombstone inscriptions, and yearbooks. The papers were originally stored in three-ring binders, but were removed for preservation purposes. Some of the photographs and negatives contained in the collection have been transferred to Special Collections.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Osterbind Family Files.
II. Haase Family Files.
III. Looper Family Files.
IV. Geschwind Family Files.
V. Subject Files.
Contents List
- Series I. Osterbind Family Files, 1845-2006., Extent: 11 boxes. (Box 1-11)
  The Osterbind family files contain information on the descendants of Clauss Osterbind (ca. 1686-1742) of Oldenburg, Germany, including Anton Guenther Bernhard Osterbind (1820-1902), and his son Henry Carter Osterbind (1851-1914). Both Anton and Henry worked at Tredegar Iron Works in Richmond. The series includes a genealogy of the Osterbind family compiled by Mary L. Geschwind in 1997, information on ancestors who resided in Germany, and the family members who emigrated to the United States, and research on the Clarke, Copeland, Jordan, and Morrison families. There is also material relating to the Osterbind family's connection with Tredegar Iron Works, including original business records from the company (1845-1865), as well as their affiliation with the Methodist Church and the Freemasons. There are also papers concerning Mary Copeland Osterbind and her years at Salem Female Academy in North Carolina, and information on her siblings Minnie Guenther Osterbind Kimball and Carter Clarke Osterbind.
  - "The Osterbind Family of Oldenburg and Richmond" by Mary L. Geschwind, 1997. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Osterbind Family - Book 1 - Ancestors - Clauss Osterbind, Sr. and Jr., Berend Osterbind, and Anton Guenther Osterbind, Sr.. (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - The Osterbind Family - Book 2 - The Emigrants - Barney A. Osterbind. (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
  - The Osterbind Family - Book 3 - The Emigrants - Annie Osterbind Hegamyer. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Osterbind Family - Book 4 - The Emigrants - Anton Guenther Osterbind. (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - The Osterbind Family - Book 5 - Copeland. (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
  - Henry Carter Osterbind/Ellen Jane Clarke - Part One. (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Henry Carter Osterbind/Ellen Jane Clarke - Part One. (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Henry Carter Osterbind/Ellen Jane Clarke - Part Two. (Box 3, Folder 5-9)
  - Henry Carter Osterbind/Ellen Jane Clarke - Part Two. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Henry Carter Osterbind/Ellen Jane Clarke - Part Three. (Box 4, Folder 2-6)
  - Henry Carter Osterbind/Ellen Jane Clarke - Part Four. (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - Henry Carter Osterbind/Ellen Jane Clarke - Part Four. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Osterbind Connection to the Tredegar Iron Works. (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
  - Anton G. and H. Carter Osterbind - Affiliation with Church and Masons. (Box 5, Folder 5-11)
  - Jordan Family. (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Jordan, Obediah. (Box 6, Folder 3-7)
  - Malcolm Morrison Family. (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
  - Morrison Family - Biggam-Eggeling Letters, 1849-1866. (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
  - John Edward Clarke and Children - Part One. (Box 7, Folder 6-10)
  - John Edward Clarke and Children - Part Two. (Box 7, Folder 11-13)
  - John Edward Clarke and Children - Part Two. (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - John Edward Clarke and Children - Part Three. (Box 8, Folder 3-7)
  - Edward Clarke/Charles Clarke. (Box 8, Folder 8-11)
  - Research Notes on Edward Clarke and His Descendants. (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
  - Mary Copeland Osterbind - Salem Female Academy. (Box 9, Folder 4-10)
  - Minnie Guenther Osterbind - Part One. (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
  - Minnie Guenther Osterbind - Part One. (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - Minnie Guenther Osterbind - Part Two. (Box 10, Folder 4-9)
  - Minnie Guenther Osterbind - Part Three. (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
  - Minnie Guenther Osterbind - Part Three. (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  - Carter Clarke Osterbind. (Box 11, Folder 59)
- Series II. Haase Family Files, 1871-2006., Extent: 14 boxes. (Box 12-24,47)
  The Haase family files document the descendants of Reinhard Haase (d. 1659) of Hildesheim, Germany, including Christian ("Charles") Gottfried Karl Haase (1828-1907), who settled in Richmond, Virginia and established a fur business in 1857. This series includes a family genealogy compiled by Mary L. Geschwind in 1998, There are also original letters, 1871-1906, between Charles and his cousin Gottlieb Karl Leopold Haase (1844-1917) of Reval, Russia, and his nephew, Wilhelm August Leopold Haase(b. 1842), of Hettstedt, Germany, the latter of whom was also in the fur business. Most of this series, however, relates to Charles' son, William Frederick Haase (1877-1967), who married Mary Copeland Osterbind (1876-1935). There is information on their childhoods, courtship, wedding and honeymoon, and their children, especially Margaret Ruppert Haase (1903-1982). The series documents family vacations, including visits to the Jamestown Exposition in 1907 and Niagara Falls in 1910, holiday celebrations, visits to and from relatives in Battle Creek, Michigan, and student life at Randolph-Macon Woman's College and the University of Virginia.
  - "The Haase Family of Hildesheim, Sandersleben, and Richmond" by Mary L. Geschwind, 1998. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Haase Genealogy. (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
  - Haase Family Database. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Charles and Lisette Haase - Haase Album One. (Box 12, Folder 5-8)
  - The Store - Charles Haase and Sons - Haase Album Two. (Box 12, Folder 9-11)
  - The Store - Charles Haase and Sons - Haase Album Two. (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - The Family - Haase Album Three, Part One. (Box 13, Folder 3-8)
  - The Family - Haase Album Three, Part Two. (Box 13, Folder 9-11)
  - Lisette Haase's Relatives - Haase Album Four. (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
  - Lisette Haase's Relatives - Haase Album Four. (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  - Charles Haase's Children - Haase Album Five, Part One. (Box 14, Folder 4-9)
  - Charles Haase's Children - Haase Album Five, Part Two. (Box 14, Folder 10-12)
  - Charles Haase's Children - Haase Album Five, Part Two. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Willie Haase and Mary Osterbind, 1870's-1902. (Box 15, Folder 2-7)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album One, 1902-1906. (Box 15, Folder 8-12)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album One, 1902-1906. (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Two. (Box 16, Folder 3-8)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Three. (Box 16, Folder 9-11)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Three. (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Four. (Box 17, Folder 4-8)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Five. (Box 17, Folder 9-11)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Five. (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Six. (Box 18, Folder 4-10)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Seven. (Box 18, Folder 11-12)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Seven. (Box 19, Folder 1-4)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Eight. (Box 19, Folder 5-11)
  - William F. Haase Family - Album Nine. (Box 20, Folder 1-9)
  - Margaret Haase - Childhood Artwork. (Box 20, Folder 10-11)
  - Margaret Haase at College and Class Notes. (Box 21, Folder 1-7)
  - William F. Haase's Boys ant Their Families. (Box 22, Folder 1-11)
  - William F. Haase's Boys ant Their Families. (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
  - Haase - Booklets. (Box 23, Folder 3-5)
  - The Haase Letters - Part One, 1871-1948. (Box 23, Folder 6-10)
  - The Haase Letters - Part Two, 1984-1998. (Box 24, Folder 1-5)
  - Haase - Ephemera. (Box 47)
- Series III. Looper Family Files, 1919-2006., Extent: 15 boxes. (Box 24-38)
  The Looper family files document the descendants of Joseph Burdine Looper (1858-1927) of Pickens County, South Carolina, specifically his son, Dr. James Burdine Looper (1899-1950), who married Margaret Ruppert Haase (1903-1982) and settled in Oxford, Mississippi. This series details student life at Furman University, the University of Virginia, and the University of Chicago, marriage, family life, Margaret's interest and involvement in music, art, gardening, genealogy, and the Daughters of the American Revolution, and Dr. Looper's career at the University of Mississippi, where he was professor and later dean of the medical school. There is a large amount of information concerning attempts to establish a four-year medical school during Dr. Looper's tenure at Ole Miss.
  - Joseph Burdine Looper Family. (Box 24, Folder 6-11)
  - Joseph Burdine Looper Family. (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album One, 1924-1927. (Box 25, Folder 3-8)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Two, August 1927-December 1928. (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Three, 1929-1930. (Box 25, Folder 10-11)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Three, 1929-1930. (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Four, 1930-1932. (Box 26, Folder 6-9)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Five, 1932-1935. (Box 26, Folder 10-11)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Five, 1932-1935. (Box 27, Folder 1-5)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Six, 1935-1938. (Box 27, Folder 6-10)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Six, 1935-1938. (Box 28, Folder 1-3)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Seven, 1938-1939. (Box 28, Folder 4-11)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Eight, 1939-1942. (Box 29, Folder 1-7)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Nine, 1942-1943. (Box 29, Folder 8-11)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Nine, 1942-1943. (Box 30, Folder 1-4)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Ten, 1944-1945. (Box 30, Folder 5-11)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Eleven, 1945. (Box 31, Folder 1-6)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Twelve, 1945-1950. (Box 31, Folder 7-11)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Twelve, 1945-1950. (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - James Burdine Looper Family - Album Thirteen, 1950-1952. (Box 32, Folder 2-10)
  - Ole Miss, 1945-1947. (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Ole Miss, 1945-1947. (Box 33, Folder 1-6)
  - Looper Workbook. (Box 33, Folder 7-9)
  - Looper Workbook. (Box 34, Folder 1-8)
  - J.B. Looper - Death, Debt, Taxes. (Box 34, Folder 9-13)
  - J.B. Looper - Death, Debt, Taxes. (Box 35, Folder 1-5)
  - Margaret Looper After 1950. (Box 35, Folder 6-12)
  - Looper - Booklets. (Box 36, Folder 1-5)
  - Untranscribed Letters - Album One. (Box 36, Folder 6-8)
  - Untranscribed Letters - Album Two. (Box 36, Folder 9-12)
  - Joseph William Looper. (Box 37, Folder 1-4)
  - Mary MacAdam Looper. (Box 37, Folder 5-11)
  - Mary MacAdam Looper. (Box 38, Folder 1-3)
  - "Looper Cousins - Descendants of Daniel Looper, Sr. of Pickens County, South Carolina". (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - "Looper Cousins - Descendants of Daniel Looper and Sarah Hester of Pickens County, South Carolina". (Box 38, Folder 5)
- Series IV. Geschwind Family Files, 1912-2006., Extent: 5 boxes. (Box 38-42)
  The Geschwind family files contain photographs and originial documents of the Geschwind and Goerke families of Germany, but a majority of the series relates to the family of Hermann Geschwind (1930-2006) and his wife Mary MacAdam Looper Geschwind (1932-2017), including their courtship at the University of Mississippi, marriage in Wiesbaden, Germany, his service in the United States Navy, graduation from the University of Richmond, and the family's relocations to Greensboro, North Carolina, and later St. Gallen, Switzerland, where he was employed with Burlington Industries. There are also files relating to their son, Carl-Henry Geschwind (b. 1965), and his school years at Grimsley Senior High in Greensboro.
  - Geschwind-Schneider Genealogy. (Box 38, Folder 6-8)
  - Geschwind Family - Documents and Pictures. (Box 38, Folder 9-11)
  - Geschwind Family - Documents and Pictures. (Box 39, Folder 1-4)
  - Goerke Family - Documents and Pictures. (Box 39, Folder 5-6)
  - Herman Geschwind Family - Album One, 1952-1954. (Box 39, Folder 7-10)
  - Herman Geschwind Family - Album One, 1952-1954. (Box 40, Folder 1-4)
  - Herman Geschwind Family - Album Two, 1953-1960. (Box 40, Folder 5-10)
  - Herman Geschwind Family - Album Two, 1952-1954. (Box 41, Folder 1-3)
  - Herman Geschwind Family - Album Three, 1960-1966. (Box 41, Folder 4-10)
  - Schweiz, 1966-1970. (Box 42, Folder 1-5)
  - Carl-Henry Geschwind, 1982-1983. (Box 42, Folder 6-9)
- Series V. Subject Files, 1932-2006., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 43-46)
  The subject files contain materials that were not originally organized or filed in three-ring binders. They relate mostly to the Haase and Looper families, and include accounts and receipts, artwork, bank statements, class notes, clippings, correspondence, estate papers of William F. Haase and Dr. James Burdine Looper, sympathy cards and notes, and taxes. Most of this series, however, are genealogical notes on various lines allied with the Osterbind, Haase, and Looper families.
  - Accounts and Receipts. (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Art and Architecture. (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Artwork. (Box 43, Folder 3-4)
  - Bank Statements. (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Biographical. (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Bridge Scorecards. (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Business Year Book. (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Check Registers. (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Class Notes (Ole Miss). (Box 43, Folder 10-11)
  - Clippings. (Box 43, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence. (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence - Dusty. (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution. (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Estate of William Frederick Haase. (Box 44, Folder 4-6)
  - Estate of Dr. James Burdine Looper. (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Garden. (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Genealogical Notes - Bates. (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Genealogical Notes - Biggam. (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Genealogical Notes - Binns. (Box 44, Folder 11)
  - Genealogical Notes - Brassieur/Brashear. (Box 44, Folder 12-13)
  - Genealogical Notes - Brush-Allen. (Box 44, Folder 14-15)
  - Genealogical Notes - Clarke (Early). (Box 44, Folder 16)
  - Genealogical Notes - Clarke, Charles. (Box 44, Folder 17)
  - Genealogical Notes - Clarke, Edward. (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Genealogical Notes - Copeland. (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Genealogical Notes - Corker. (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Genealogical Notes - DuVal. (Box 45, Folder 4-5)
  - Genealogical Notes - Fleming. (Box 45, Folder 6-8)
  - Genealogical Notes - Frazer. (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - Genealogical Notes - Haase. (Box 45, Folder 10)
  - Genealogical Notes - Hegamyer. (Box 45, Folder 11)
  - Genealogical Notes - Jordan. (Box 45, Folder 12)
  - Genealogical Notes - Jordan, Obediah. (Box 45, Folder 13)
  - Genealogical Notes - Jordan, Samuel. (Box 45, Folder 14)
  - Genealogical Notes - Morrison. (Box 45, Folder 15)
  - Genealogical Notes - Nuckols. (Box 45, Folder 16)
  - Genealogical Notes - Osterbind. (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Genealogical Notes - Pearce/Pierce. (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Genealogical Notes - Randolph/Pleasants. (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Genealogical Notes - Stodghill/Miller. (Box 46, Folder 4-5)
  - Genealogical Notes - Tarleton. (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Genealogical Notes - Woodson. (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Genealogy. (Box 46, Folder 8)
  - Greeting Cards. (Box 46, Folder 9)
  - Historic Sites. (Box 46, Folder 10)
  - Mary Buie Museum. (Box 46, Folder 11)
  - Medical/Health. (Box 46, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum Book. (Box 46, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 46, Folder 14)
  - The Mississippi Doctor. (Box 46, Folder 15)
  - Postcards. (Box 46, Folder 16)
  - Recipes. (Box 46, Folder 17)
  - RMWC Today, 1958. (Box 46, Folder 18)
  - Sympathy Cards and Notes. (Box 46, Folder 19)
  - Taxes. (Box 46, Folder 20-21)
  - Will of Margaret Haase Looper. (Box 46, Folder 22)